Website privacy notice
----------------------

_**Data Controller**:_

_Stiftelsen Flowminder_  
_Magnus Ladulåsgatan 1, 118 65 Stockholm, Sweden_

_Email:_ [_gdpr@flowminder.org_](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org)

This privacy notice tells you when and how Flowminder Foundation collects personal information. It contains information for:

* Visitors to our website
* People emailing us or submitting via the contact form on our website to make an inquiry, request information or services, e.g. who contact us to request a publication, report, concept note, or scope of work from us
* Job applicants

### General information

The first part of this notice contains information that is applicable to everybody visiting our website.

#### Embedded links to other websites

This privacy notice does not cover the links embedded within the text contained on this website linking you to other websites. We encourage you to read the privacy statements on those and other websites that you visit.

#### Changes to this privacy notice

We regularly review our privacy notice. This privacy notice was last updated on 02 July 2021.

### Visitors to our website

_**Person responsible for website visitors data protection**: [gdpr@flowminder.org](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org)._

We have developed our [www.flowminder.org](https://www.flowminder.org/ "Home") website so that you can visit it without registering and we do not make any attempt to find out the identities of those visiting our website.

#### Use of cookies by Flowminder Foundation

The cookies tools on our website rely on implied consent of users. In recognition of the fact that the implementation date for the revised e-Privacy Regulation remains unknown, we are taking reasonable steps now to align our use of cookies to the standard of consent required by GDPR.

‘Cookies’ are small text files placed on your computer, smartphone, or similar, by most websites. Cookies allow the website to recognise the device used to access the website and record information about visitors activities and preferences in order to improve the website’s functionality and user experience. You can read our full cookies policy here and also find information on how to manage your cookies settings.

Our [www.flowminder.org](https://www.flowminder.org/ "Home") website uses four separate Cookies. Three are installed by a third-party service, called Google Analytics, to collect standard internet log information and details of visitor behavior patterns. These are:

_\_ga (visitor tracking)_  
_\_gid (session id)_  
_\_gat (throttling)_

Together, these cookies allow us to find out such things as the number of visitors to the various parts of the site. This information is processed in a way that does not identify anyone.

We have installed a fourth, first-party cookie, placed on the www.flowminder.org website by us for the functioning of the website. It is:

_EtchCookieConsent_

This cookie hides the cookie information section once this has been seen.

### People who email us to make an inquiry or request information or services

Person responsible for service users data protection: [gdpr@flowminder.org](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org).

When you email the organisation ([info@flowminder.org](mailto:info@flowminder.org)) or submit via the contact form on our website to make an inquiry or request that we provide information or services we retain the email and the contact form submission (containing personal data relating to your name and email address) in order to provide the information or service you have requested.

#### What information does the organisation collect?

* Your email address
* Your name
* Your affiliation (if provided in the email you send us)
* Your profession and job title (if provided in the email you send us)

#### Why does the organisation process personal data?

The organisation has a legitimate interest in processing your data in order to respond to your inquiry or request. We only process the personal data contained in your email or contact form submission, for example your name and email address, in order to provide the information or service you have requested. We do not process the contact details provided for any purpose other than delivering the requested information and / or services.

#### Who has access to data?

Your information will be shared internally for the direct and sole purpose of delivering the requested information and / or services. This includes members of the organisations administration team and research staff with expertise in the field of your inquiry.

We will not share any personal data that you disclose to us in your email or contact form submission, such as your name or email address, with any third party except for our suppliers that work on our behalf to enable our email service and form.

#### How does the organisation protect data?

The organisation takes the security of your data seriously. It has internal policies and controls in place to ensure that your data is not lost, accidentally destroyed, misused or disclosed, and is not accessed except by our employees in the proper performance of their duties.  
We do not automatically encrypt and protect email or contact form traffic received via our website. You should be aware that any emails you send may not be protected in transit unless you take measures to encrypt or otherwise protect their contents.

#### For how long does the organisation keep data?

We retain emails sent to the info@flowminder.org address via the website for up to six months from the date of inquiry. This is to assist us to manage any follow-up request you may have.

#### Your rights

As a data subject, you have a number of rights. You can:

* access and obtain a copy of your data on request;
* require the organisation to change incorrect or incomplete data;
* require the organisation to delete or stop processing your data, for example where the data is no longer necessary for the purposes of processing;
* object to the processing of your data where the organisation is relying on its legitimate interests as the legal ground for processing; and
* ask the organisation to stop processing data for a period if data is inaccurate or there is a dispute about whether or not your interests override the organisation's legitimate grounds for processing data.

If you would like to exercise any of these rights, please contact [gdpr@flowminder.org](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org).

If you believe that the organisation has not complied with your data protection rights, you can complain to the Information Commissioner.

Website Cookies Policy
======================

_**Data Controller**:  Stiftelsen Flowminder, Magnus Ladulåsgatan 1, Stockholm, Sweden_  
Email: [gdpr@flowminder.org](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org)

Use of cookies by Flowminder Foundation
---------------------------------------

The cookies tools on our website rely on implied consent of users.  In recognition of the fact that the implementation date for the revised e-Privacy Regulation remains unknown, we are taking reasonable steps now to align our use of cookies to the standard of consent required by GDPR.

‘Cookies’ are small text files placed on your computer, smartphone, or similar, by most websites. Cookies allow the website to recognise the device used to access the website and record information about visitors activities and preferences in order to improve the website’s functionality and user experience.

Our [www.flowminder.org](http://www.flowminder.org/) website uses four separate Cookies. Three are installed by a third-party service, called Google Analytics, to collect standard internet log information and details of visitor behavior patterns. These are:

_\_ga (visitor tracking)_  
_\_gid (session id)_  
_\_gat (throttling)_

Together, these Cookies allow us to find out such things as the number of visitors to the various parts of the site. This information is processed in a way that does not identify anyone.

We have installed a fourth, first-party cookie, placed on the http://www.flowminder.org website by us for the functioning of the website. It is:

_EtchCookieConsent_

This cookie only lasts for the unique session of a visitor, and is removed when the visitor closes their browser. No personal data is collected.

|     |     |     |
| --- | --- | --- |
| Cookie | Name | Purpose |
| Cookie preference | EtchCookieConsent | This cookie hides the cookie information section once this has been seen. |
| Google Analytics | \_ga (visitor tracking)  <br>\_gid (session id)  <br>\_gat (throttling) | These cookies are used to collect information about how visitors use our website. We use the information to compile reports and to help us improve the website.  <br>The cookies collect information in an anonymous form, including the number of visitors to the website and blog, where visitors have come to the website from and the pages they visited.  <br>Read Google's overview of privacy and safeguarding data [here](https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245). |
| TBC | TBC | This cookie is used to improve website functioning. It only lasts for the unique session of a visitor, and is removed when the visitor closes their browser. No personal data is collected. |

#### How to change your cookies settings

Most web browsers permit users to control aspects of most cookies through their browser settings. To find out more about cookies, including how to see what cookies have been set, visit www.aboutcookies.org or www.allaboutcookies.org.

#### How to manage cookies settings on the most common internet browsers

You can follow the hyper-links below for guidance on how to manage your cookies settings:

Job Applicant Privacy Notice
----------------------------

This Privacy Notice was last updated on 20th November 2024.

|     |     |
| --- | --- |
| **Data Controller:** <br><br>  <br><br>Stiftelsen Flowminder<br><br>Box: 4250, 102 65, Stockholm, Sweden<br><br>Email: [gdpr@flowminder.org](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org) | Data Protection Officer:<br><br>  <br><br>Bird and Bird Privacy Solutions<br><br>Avenue Louise 235 Box 1<br><br>1050 Brussels<br><br>Belgium<br><br>T: +32 (0) 2282 6000<br><br>[DPO.Flowminder@twobirds.com](mailto:DPO.Flowminder@twobirds.com) |

### Introduction

Flowminder is committed to protecting the privacy and security of your personal data during the recruitment process. As the “Data Controller”, we are responsible for deciding how we hold and use personal data about you. This notice outlines how we comply with our data protection obligations and seek to protect the personal information of our job applicants. Its purpose is to make you aware of how and why we are using your personal data and what your rights are under data protection legislation.

We recognise the need to treat the personal data we hold about you in an appropriate manner and process it in accordance with the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) (EU) 2016/679 as it forms part of domestic law in the United Kingdom by virtue of section 3 of the European Union (Withdrawal) Act 2018 and [DPPEC (Data Protection, Privacy and Electronic Communications (Amendment Etc.) (EU Exit)) Regulations 2019](https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.legislation.gov.uk%2Fuksi%2F2019%2F419%2Fcontents%2Fmade&data=04%7C01%7CC.J.Trotter%40soton.ac.uk%7C24ba064afdf04e74e73208d8d8a218de%7C4a5378f929f44d3ebe89669d03ada9d8%7C0%7C0%7C637497537992438487%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C1000&sdata=3aVLzIdeRyYdOJO8LwIBVtC5K6aTkP07piqSyUUG8Uo%3D&reserved=0) (including as further amended or modified by the laws of the United Kingdom or of a part of the United Kingdom from time to time) (UK GDPR) and the UK Data Protection Act (DPA) 2018.

Personal data refers to the information that we hold about you from which either on its own or in combination with other information you can be identified and may include names, contact details, photographs, identification numbers, online identifiers, and expressions of opinion about you, or person-specific indications as to our intentions about you. A non-exhaustive list of the types of personal data we collect is set out in this notice.

"Processing" means doing anything with your personal data, such as collecting, recording or holding the personal data as well as disclosing, destroying or using the personal data in any way.

### Data protection principles

We keep data protection law and its principles at the centre of Flowminder. This means that any personal data we do collect must be:

* Used lawfully, fairly and in a transparent way
* Collected only for valid purposes that we have clearly explained to you and not used in any way that is incompatible with those purposes
* Relevant to the purposes we have told you about and limited only to those purposes
* Accurate and kept up to date
* Kept only as long as necessary for the purposes we have told you about
* Kept securely

### Why does Flowminder process your personal data?

We process your personal data to enable us to process your job application and to complete the recruitment process. The table below details our specific purposes for processing your personal data and the lawful basis that applies to that purpose for processing.

|     |     |     |
| --- | --- | --- |
| Purpose | Type of personal data processed | Lawful basis for processing |
| To ensure effective communication during the recruitment process, including interview scheduling and application updates | Communication information, such as your personal email address and telephone number | Legitimate Interests (Article 6(1)(f)) - Necessary for the management of the recruitment process and communication with you |
| To offer a job and manage the hiring process before the employment contract is finalised | Communication information, such as your personal email address and telephone number | Performance of a Contract (Article 6(1)(b)) – Where a job offer is made, processing is required to take the necessary steps before entering into a contract. |
| To assess your suitability for the role | Name, contact information, work experience, qualifications | Performance of a Contract (Article 6(1)(b)) – Processing is required to take steps at your request before entering into a contract. |
| To work with recruitment agencies to source candidates | Name, contact information, employment data, education data, skills | Legitimate Interests (Article 6(1)(f)) – Necessary for our recruitment process to identify and evaluate potential candidates. |
| To verify your identity, age and right to work in the UK | Identification data, right to work information (including passports and visas) and contact information | Legal Obligation (Article 6(1)(c)) – Compliance with immigration and employment laws, such as the Immigration, Asylum, and Nationality Act 2006. |
| To comply with anti-terrorism, sanctions, and financial crime legislation and ensure the integrity and security of the workforce | Full name | Performance of a Contract (Article 6(1)(b)) - Required to fulfil our contractual obligations with donors and other third parties we work with, and as part of the recruitment process in complying with the contract |
| To make reasonable adjustments for candidates with disabilities, e.g. providing an interpreter for a hearing-impaired candidate during the interview or modifying the physical workspace for candidates with mobility impairments | Identification data, special category data (disability status, nature of the disability or medical condition, specific support or adjustment needs), interview data | Legal Obligation (Article 6(1)(c)) – Required to fulfil our legal obligations under disability discrimination laws<br><br>Employment, social security and social protection law (Article 9(2)(b) -  Allows us to process special category data for this purpose |
| To monitor equal opportunities and diversity within the recruitment process | Equal opportunities data, e.g. ethnic origin, disability status, religion | Consent (Article 6(1)(a))<br><br>Explicit Consent (Article 9(2)(a) -  Allows us to process special category data for this purpose |
| To maintain records for compliance and audit purposes | Identification data, recruitment data, assessment data, eligibility data | Legal Obligation (Article 6(1)(c)) – Complying with employment and data protection laws. |
| To retain your data for future job opportunities | Identification data, recruitment data, assessment data, eligibility data | Legitimate Interests (Article 6(1)(f)) |
| To support the bringing or defense of legal claims in the event of recruitment related disputes | Special category data (health data, disability status, etc.) | Legitimate Interests (Article 6(1)(f)) - To protect our legal interests and ensure that we can appropriately manage disputes and legal proceedings<br><br>Establishment, Exercise or Defence of Legal Claims (Article 9(2)(f) -  Allows us to process special category data for this purpose |

We will only process your personal data for the specific purpose or purposes that we tell you about or if specifically permitted under any privacy legislation and will only process your personal data to the extent necessary for that specific purpose or purposes.

### Personal data we collect

During the recruitment process, the organisation collects a range of information about you. This includes:

* **Identification data:** Your name, address and contact details, including email address and telephone number, date of birth and gender
* **Application data:** Details of your qualifications, skills, experience and employment history
* **Financial data:** Details of your bank account where you have chosen payment to be made and your National Insurance Number
* **Assessment data:** Interview notes, skills tests and other evaluation materials
* **Sensitive data:** Whether or not you have a disability for which the organisation needs to make reasonable adjustments during the recruitment process and equal opportunities monitoring information, including information about your ethnic origin, sexual orientation, health, and religion or beliefs
* **Data regarding your entitlement to work in the UK:** Passport (including the photo page and any relevant visa pages), visa or work permit details, other supporting evidence if required, such as your birth certificate, Proof of Indefinite Leave to Remain (ILR) or marriage or civil partnership certificate where applicable

### How does Flowminder use your Special Category Personal Data?

Special Category Data is personal data that the data protection legislation says is more sensitive, and so needs more protection. It includes information about an individual’s race, ethnic origins, politics, religion, trade union membership, genetics, biometrics (where used for unique identification purposes), health, sex life, or sexual orientation. 

Some special categories of personal data, such as information about health or medical conditions, are processed to carry out employment law obligations (such as those in relation to employees with disabilities).

Where we process other special categories of your personal data, such as information about ethnic origin, sexual orientation, or religion or other beliefs, this is done for limited necessary purposes, including equal opportunities monitoring.

We do not need your consent if we use special categories of your personal data to carry out our legal obligations or exercise specific rights in the field of employment law. In limited circumstances, we may approach you for your written consent to allow us to process certain particularly sensitive data. If we do so, we will provide you with full details of the data that we would like to process and the reason, so that you can carefully consider whether you wish to consent. You are under no obligation to provide data for equal opportunities monitoring purposes and there are no consequences for your application if you choose not to provide such data. 

We may collect and process special categories of your personal data in the following circumstances:

* In limited circumstances where absolutely necessary on the basis of your written consent obtained in advance of the processing activity
* Where it is needed to support the bringing or defense of legal claims in the event of disputes relating to the recruitment process 
* Where you have already manifestly made special categories of personal data public

We will collect and use the following particular types of your personal data of a specific special category nature in the following ways:

* We will use information about your physical or mental health, or disability status, to ensure your health and safety and provide appropriate adjustments should you be invited to interview
* With your consent, we may collect and use data about your race, national or ethnic origin, religious, philosophical, or moral beliefs, and/or your sexual life or sexual orientation, to ensure meaningful equal opportunity monitoring and reporting. Such data will be aggregated with other job applicants’ data so that you are not personally identifiable to any third-party organisation with which we share this information. You can withdraw your consent at any time, and there are no consequences if you choose not to provide such data

### What if you decide not to provide us with your personal data?

You are under no statutory or contractual obligation to provide your personal data to us during the recruitment process. However, if you do choose not to provide the information, we may not be able to process your application properly or at all.

You are under no obligation to provide information for equal opportunities monitoring purposes and there are no consequences for your application if you choose not to provide such information.

### How will we collect your personal data?

We may collect your personal data in a variety of ways. For example, personal information might be collected directly from you (through application forms, CVs or resumes); obtained from your passport or other identity documents such as your driving licence (for identity authentication purposes); from correspondence with you; or through interviews, or other meetings and assessments that form part of the recruitment activity.

We may also collect personal data about you from third parties, such as references supplied by former employers (nominated by you), UK Visa and Immigration, information from employment background check providers and information supplied to us from external recruitment agencies.

We will usually only seek information from third parties once a job offer to you has been made and will inform you that we are doing so.

We will always look to ensure that any third party has the lawful authority to share this personal data with us.

### Working with recruitment agencies

We work with Pure Human Resources, a trusted recruitment agency, to assist us in sourcing and evaluating candidates for roles within our organisation. As part of their services, Pure Human Resources may share your personal data with us if you have applied through them or have been identified as a potential candidate.

#### Data we receive from Pure Human Resources

We may receive the following information from Pure Human Resources:

* Your name, contact details, and CV.
* Employment history, qualifications, and other details relevant to your application or suitability for a role.

Pure Human Resources is an independent data controller and is responsible for ensuring that your personal data is processed lawfully before sharing it with us. For details on how Pure Human Resources processes your data, please refer to their privacy notice.

### Who has access to the data?

Your information will be shared internally for the purposes of the recruitment exercise. This includes members of the HR and recruitment team, interviewers involved in the recruitment process, managers in the business area with a vacancy and IT staff if access to the data is necessary for the performance of their roles.

The organisation will not share your data with third parties, unless your application for employment is successful and it makes you an offer of employment. The organisation will then share your data with former employers to obtain references for you.

Your data will not be transferred outside the European Economic Area (EEA) as we store all data in the cloud, where the data residency is within the EEA.

### How does the organisation protect data?

The organisation takes the security of your data seriously. It has internal policies and controls in place to ensure that your data is not lost, accidentally destroyed, misused or disclosed, and is not accessed except by our employees in the proper performance of their duties.

### For how long does the organisation keep data?

If your application for employment is unsuccessful, we will hold your data on file for twelve months after the end of the relevant recruitment process. If you wish for us to delete this data, you can request this at any time by contacting [gdpr@flowminder.org](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org)

If your application for employment is successful, personal data gathered during the recruitment process will be transferred to your personnel file and retained during your employment. The periods for which your data will be held will be provided to you in a new privacy notice.

### Your rights

As a data subject, you have a number of rights. You can:

* Access and obtain a copy of your data on request
* Require the organisation to change incorrect or incomplete data
* Require the organisation to delete or stop processing your data, for example where the data is no longer necessary for the purposes of processing
* Object to the processing of your data where the organisation is relying on its legitimate interests as the legal ground for processing
* Ask the organisation to stop processing data for a period if data is inaccurate or there is a dispute about whether or not your interests override the organisation's legitimate grounds for processing data
* Have the right to data portability
* Withdraw your consent to the processing of your personal data at any time

If you would like to exercise any of these rights, please contact [gdpr@flowminder.org](mailto:gdpr@flowminder.org)

If you believe that the organisation has not complied with your data protection rights, you can make a complaint to the Information Commissioner.

### Automated decision-making

Recruitment processes are not based on automated decision-making.
